Email: simon.mwaura957@gmail.com Website — Linkedin — Github — Medium Mobile: +23058417727

SUMMARY

Electrical Engineering graduate with multidisciplinary experience spanning power systems, automation, data science, and energy innovation. Adept at solving complex technical challenges through a systems-thinking approach. Strong programming background with proven leadership in team projects, consulting, and entrepreneurial ventures. Open to roles in energy systems, automation, data analytics, and interdisciplinary problem solving in both technical and business-focused environments.

EDUCATION

Glasgow Caledonian University

Glasgow, UK

BEng(Hons) Electrical Power Engineering

Sept 2021 - Dec 2024

o Relevant modules: Renewable Integration, Power Systems, Control Engineering, Energy Audit and Management, Modeling and Data Analysis

African Leadership University

Pamplemousses, MU

Leadership Core

Jan 2021 - Aug 2021

• Relevant modules: Project management, Entrepreneurial Leadership, Communication for Impact

Experience

ALU Consulting Club

Pamplemousses, MU

Freelance Researcher and Data Analyst

Oct 2022 - Present

- Leveraged analytical, research, and programming skills to perform comprehensive market, technical and financial feasibility studies for startups and SMEs.
- Applied modeling techniques to enhance decision-making pipelines for local businesses and student ventures, improving operational efficiency.

Energy Innovation Capital

Remote

Research Intern

Mar 2023 - May 2023

- Conducted market analysis and prepared reports on emerging energy technologies and industry trends.
- o Contributed to investment strategy planning by providing insights on breakthrough technologies in VC landscapes.
- Developed research skills specific to the energy and investment sector.

Aqua Springs Limited

Moka, MU

Programmable Logic Controllers Trainee

Apr 2022 - Aug 2022

- Assisted senior engineers in maintaining PLC programs for the plant processes, ensuring consistent quality.
- Troubleshot and optimised logic in PLC programs, minimising operations downtime.
- o Gained hands-on experience with industrial automation and control systems.

$INCOGNITO^{TM}$

Solo-preneur

Pamplemousses, MU

Aug 2021 - Present

- Built and ran a personal merchandise brand, selling over 400 uniquely branded items.
- Partnered with local businesses on design/branding projects

Equity Bank Limited

Nairobi, KE

Relationships Officer

Feb 2019 - Sept 2019

- Improved customer service efficiency, reducing waiting times by 30% while serving 200+ customers daily.
- Contributed to a 73.8% consumer satisfaction index by resolving digital mobile banking issues

Projects

• E-waste Management

- Led a team to develop an on-campus e-waste reduction program, refurbishing 130+ electronic devices and boosting recovery by 30%.
- Collaborated with university administration to integrate the initiative into sustainability programs.

• Smart Traffic Control System

- \circ Led a team of 3 in designing an AI-based adaptive signal control prototype.
- Reducing simulated urban wait times by 5%.
- o Tools: OpenCV, TensorFlow

• Electricity Demand Forecasting

 \circ Developed a deep learning model with Python, Keras and TensorFlow to forecast electricity demand, improving accuracy by 7.3%.

SKILLS

- Technical: Python, C++, SQL, MATLAB, Arduino, 3D Printing, PLC programming
- Soft & Transferable: Analytical Thinking, Leadership, Project Management, Communication, Research, Systems Thinking

Relevant Certifications

- Financial Markets Yale University
- Exploring Renewable Energy Schemes University of Pennsylvania
- Advanced Learning Algorithms DeepLearning.AI
- Supervised Machine Learning DeepLearning.AI
- Sequences, Time Series and Prediction DeepLearning.AI

Interests

• Systems Theory, AI applications, Finance & VC, Soccer, Chess